Finding aid to the Carole A. Oglesby papers SSC.MS.00492
Sophia Smith Collection
Carole A. Oglesby papers
1950-2017
Sophia Smith Collection
Oglesby, Carole A.
SSC.MS.00492
119.5 linear feet (89 record cartons, 1 letter size document box, 1 half letter size document box, 4 oversize boxes, and 1 flat file)
Carole A. Oglesby was one of the pioneers in the women's sports movement from the 1950s through the 1990s and was also one of the first "out" lesbians in U.S. athletics. The bulk of this collection represents Carole Oglesby's professional activities and research, and as such, it contains materials related to the subject of women and sport from the 1960s to the early 2000s.
Conditions Governing Access
The most recent accessions for this collection are open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections. Per the terms of the deed of gift, this colleciton is "closed until fully processed," so the contents of the 2003 donation remain closed at this time.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this resource were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Carole A. Oglesby in three groups in 2003 and 2018 (accessions 03S-70, 2018-A-0001, and 2018-A-0007).
Biographical Note
Carole A. Oglesby was one of the pioneers in the women's sports movement from the 1950s through the 1990s and was also one of the first "out" lesbians in U.S. athletics.
Oglesby earned her A.B. and her M.S. in physical education at the University of California, Los Angeles, in 1961 and 1964 respectively; in 1969 she received her Ph.D. from Purdue University. She served as the first president of the Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (AIAW), and as the first president of Women Sport International; she opposed the merger of the AIAW with the National Collegiate Athletic Association in 1982.
Oglesby has served as president of the National Association for Girls and Women in Sport, and as trustee for the Women's Sports Foundation (WSF). She organized WSF's "The New Agenda" conference, which set the research agenda for women in sport in the early 1980s; one of the most serious issues encountered at this conference involved homophobia in sport. She also served on the Executive Committee of the United States Collegiate Sports Council for twenty-five years, an arm of the International Federation of University Sport, which organizes the World University Games.
Oglesby wrote "Women in Sport: From Myth to Reality"; was the editor of the Encyclopedia of Women in Sport in America, as well as several other monographs; and authored hundreds of articles, book chapters, and book reviews. She has also been the editor of several journals relating to education, sport, sex roles, and psychology.
Oglesby has travelled the globe, explicating the connection between women's sports and women's rights, and she serves as a consultant to many athletic and women's groups. After nearly forty years of teaching at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst, Purdue University, and Temple University, Oglesby went back to school to earn a Ph.D. in Counseling Psychology at Temple University. She is certified as a trained practitioner in eye movement desensitisation reprocessing, and taught at California State University, Northridge, where she headed the department of kinesiology. Oglesby currently serves as the International Policy and Program Advisor for the Women's Sports Foundation.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this collection represents Carole Oglesby's professional activities and research, and as such, it contains materials related to the subject of women and sport from the 1960s to the early 2000s.
Subtopics include homophobia in sport, racial awareness in women's sport, Title IX, the relationship between women's sport and feminism, and international women's conferences. Organizations represented in the collection include the American Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance; National Association for Girls and Women in Sport; United States Olympic Committee; United States Collegiate Sports Council; International Federation of University Sport (IFUS); American Association for Applied Sports Psychology; Commission on the Status of Women; and the Women's Sports Foundation. Projects and conferences in the collection include the New Agenda, a conference planning the future of research in women's sport; the COACH project, which worked with Pennsylvania high school coaches; the 1977 Torch Run to Houston; and International Women's Year. The collection also contains a small amount of student and administration files from Temple University and the University of Massachusetts at Amherst; and Oglesby's financial records, correspondence, and manuscripts. It also contains some materials originally belonging to Christine Shelton, related to women and sport.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. The unprocessed 2003 accession has an unpublished container list that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
African American women athletes--History--20th century--Sources; Lesbian athletes--History--20th century--Sources; Homophobia in sports--History--20th century--Sources; Physical education for women--History--20th century--Sources; Physical education teachers--History--20th century--Sources; Sports for women--History--20th century--Sources; Oglesby, Carol A.; American Association for Health, Physical Education, and Recreation. Division for Girls and Women's Sports--History--Sources; American Association of University Professors--History--Sources; Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women--History--Sources; International Women's Year, 1975; National Association for Girls and Women in Sport--History--Sources; Temple University--Faculty--History--Sources; United Nations Commission on the Status of Women--History--Source; Women's Sports Foundation--History--Sources; Women and Sport, Title IX, United States Collegiate Sports Council, AAASP, Commission on the Status of Women, The New Agenda, COACH project, 1977 Torch Run; Shelton, Christine; Agendas; Appointment books; Audiotapes; Awards; Bibliographies; Books; Brochures; Business cards; Buttons (information artifacts); Bylaws; clippings; correspondence; Electronic mail; Faxes; Financial records; Interviews; Invoices; lecture notes; Manuscripts; memorabilia; Minutes; Memorandums; Newsletters; newspaper clippings; Research; Pamphlets; Periodicals; photographs; press releases; reports; Resolutions; Sheet music; Speeches; Theses; Writings; Oglesby, Carole A.
- Carole A. Oglesby papers, 1964-2003; 2003-S-0040; 79 linear feet (69 record cartons, plus oversize boxes and flat files)
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is "closed until fully processed" per the terms of the deed of gift.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of the unprocessed accession of materials given by Carole Oglesby in 2003.
  The bulk of this accession contains materials related to the subject of women and sport from the 1960s to the early 2000s. Subtopics include homophobia in sport, racial awareness in women's sport, Title IX, the relationship between women's sport and feminism, and international women's conferences. Organizations include the American Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance; National Association for Girls and Women in Sport; United States Olympic Committee; United States Collegiate Sports Council; International Federation of University Sport (IFUS); American Association for Applied Sports Psychology; Commission on the Status of Women; and the Women's Sports Foundation. Projects and conferences include the New Agenda, a conference planning the future of research in women's sport; the COACH project, which worked with Pennsylvania high school coaches; the 1977 Torch Run to Houston; and International Women's Year. Other materials include student and administration files of Temple University and the University of Massachusetts at Amherst; and Oglesby's financial records, correspondence, and manuscripts. Contains a box or two of materials appearing to belong to Christine Shelton, related to women and sport.
  Other Finding Aids
  A box list for this series, created at the time of accessioning, can be sent to you upon request.
- Carole A. Oglesby papers addition, 1950-2016; 2018-S-0001; 20.75 linear feet (15 record cartons, 1 flat box, 1 full size letter document box, 1 flat folder); 3 items (3 CDs); 17 items (17 VHS cassette tapes)
  This accession containst information and materials from the various women's sports organizations Oglesby was a member of, materials from courses she took and taught, materials from lectures and presentations, publications, media, and conference materials. It also includes personal correspondence, photographs, and other items, such as Oglesby's course work both as an undergraduate and graduate student.
  Separated Materials
  One record carton of books, not by or about Oglesby, were donated to the Northampton League of Women Voters for their annual book fair.
  Videotapes; CDs
  - Email printouts (personal and miscellaneous), 1995-2013 (Box 1)
  - Beyond Sport correspondence, 2009-2014 (Box 1)
  - Women's health correspondence, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Racism and racism in sports education, 1992-1998; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Gender equality, 1979-1992 (Box 2)
  - Sexual harrassment, 1994-2005 (Box 2)
  - Violence Against Women conference, Los Angeles, 2007-2010; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Gold sport shorts, approximately 1955-1965 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1953 (Box 3)
  - Varsity letter patches, approximately 1950-1960 (Box 3)
  - Personal cards, 1995-2005 (Box 3)
  - Medals, 1950s (Box 3)
  - Personal photos, 1994-1999; 2 folders (2 envelopes) (Box 3)
  - United Nations materials related to women in sports, 1995-2008; 14 folders (14 folders) (Box 4)
  - WomenSport International (WSI) and International Working Group on Women in Sport (IWG) papers, 1981-2014; 15 folders (15 folders) (Box 5)
  - Carole Oglesby dissertation and research, 1998; 13 folders (13 folders) (Box 6)
    Includes articles, notes, correspondence, and drafts about Carole Oglesby's doctoral dissertation from Temple University.
  - Sports psychology graduate program papers, 1995-1999; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Sports psychology files, approximately 1990-2000 (Box 6)
  - N.A.S. papers and nomination communications, 2001-2002 (Box 7)
  - "Image Quest" weight program, 1991; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 7)
  - California State University, Northridge (CSUN) papers, 2004-2011; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 7)
  - Citizen Ambassadors program, 1995 (Box 7)
  - Association for Applied Sport Psychology (AASP) papers, 2001; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 7)
  - Various publications, 1975-2000 (Box 8)
  - "Encyclopedia of Women and Sport in America" drafts, correspondence, and notes, 1998; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Presentation and lecture materials, 1995-2002; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 8)
  - Undergraduate course work and sports psych, 1960-1977; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 8)
  - PE classes, 1975 (Box 8)
  - UMass papers, 1974 (Box 8)
  - Internship papers, 1992 (Box 8)
  - Women's Sport Foundation (WSF) papers, 1987-2005; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - International Working Group on Women and Sport (IWG) papers, 1991-2014; 15 folders (15 folders) (Box 9)
  - Psychology training, 1973-1993; 16 folders (16 folders) (Box 10)
  - Email printouts, 2005-2010; 13 folders (13 folders) (Box 11)
  - Various publications and notes, 1981-2007; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Soroptimist notes, published information, and conference papers, 2005-2009; 9 folders (8 folders and 1 binder) (Box 12)
  - Correspondence about WSI, conferences, task forces, Soroptimist, 1997-2001; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 12)
  - Olympics papers, 1997-2002; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - American Alliance for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance (AAHPERD) papers, 2012-2013 (Box 13)
  - "Women and Sport: The Long Road Up" radio program, 2016; 1 folders (Box 13)
  - Email printouts concerning lectures, 1996-2007 (Box 13)
  - UN Women and Sport, 2003-2006; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Various organization papers, 1996-2016; 14 folders (14 folders) (Box 13)
  - Publications, 1970s-1990s; 2 folders (1 regular and 1 legal folder) (Box 14)
  - Temple University papers, 1995-2003; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 14)
  - 2004 Pre-Olympics final program, AASP 2002 Conference proceedings, Ending Violence Against Women policy summit 2008, IOC World Conference on Sports Sciences 1989, AAHPERD National Convention and Exposition 1992, Innovations in Sports Psychology program and proceedings 1997, ISSP 11th World Congress of Sports Psychology 2005, IOC Conference on Women and Sport 2000, American Psychological Association 98th Annual Convention 1990, NGO CSW Forum 2013 and 2014, 16th International Symposium of Adapted Physical Activity proceedings 2007, International Society of Sport Psychology program 2001, International Women and Sport conference 2007, 1990-2014; 31 items (31 books of various sizes) (Box 15)
  - Conference materials and periodicals, 1975-1995; 40 items (40 items) (Box 16)
  - Book with articles by or reference to Carole Oglesby, approximately 1980-2010; 5 items (5 items) (Box 16)
  - Photocopies of book inscriptions and acknowledgements, 1994-2009; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 16)
  - 1995 Pan Am Games, Team USA Memories: Mar Del Plata, Argentina VHS tape (Box 17)
  - PE 531: Temple University Softball, Group Dynamic VHS tape, 1993; 1 Cassettes (Box 17)
  - PE 205: Mindset for Winning VHS tape, 1996 (Box 17)
  - Benetton Sportsystem: Sports-Talk Series VHS tape, 1994 (Box 17)
  - A Tale of "O": On Being Different VHS tape (used in C. Oglesby's Psych 181 class), 1973 (Box 17)
  - Shenyang, China trip VHS tape, 1993 (Box 17)
  - A Sporting Chance Foundation VHS tape, 1986 (Box 17)
  - Princeton VHS tapes 1-3, 1990; 3 Cassettes (Box 17)
  - WomenSport Foundation (WSF) VHS tape, approximately 1990 (Box 17)
  - The Changer: A Record of the Times VHS tape, 1991 (Box 17)
  - AAHPERD tapes 3, 51, 54, 102, and 142, approximately 1993-2003; 5 audiocassettes (5 audio cassette tapes) (Box 17)
  - Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (AIAW) reunion CD, 2009 (Box 17)
  - Master Planning Committee: Carole Oglesby presentation, approximately 1993-2003 (Box 17)
  - International Society of Sports Psychology 11th World Congress CD, 2005 (Box 17)
  - Oversize posters and calendar pages, 1992-2005; 18 items (18 items) (Folder 1)
- Carole A. Oglesby papers further addition, 1955-2003; 2018-S-0007; 14.75 linear feet (9 record cartons, 1 flat box)
  This accession, like previous ones, contains materials related to the subject of women and sport from the 1960s to the present day. It contains information and materials from the various women's sports organizations Oglesby was a member of, materials from courses she took and taught, materials from lectures and presentations, publications, media, and conference materials. Also includes personal correspondence, photographs, and items.
  Three record cartons of material created by/related to Christine M. Shelton were added to her papers held by the Sophia Smith Collection.
  - PE class materials, 1986-1999; 18 folders (18 folders); Notes on lectures, class discussion, articles, and assignment responses for PE 630, PE 607, PE 5, PE 4, PE 205, and PE 531 (Box 1)
  - Rorschach class materials, Summer 1989; 1 folders (1 legal folder) (Box 1)
  - Purdue University materials, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - Various organization materials, 1983-2001 (Box 2)
    Several folders of material from WSF, NAIA, Mindset Inc., QUEST, and the US Olympic Committee
  - Association for Applied Sport Psychology (AASP) conference materials, 1986-1993 (Box 2)
  - WomenSport Foundation (WSF) papers, 1985-2003 (Box 2)
  - International Working Group on Women in Sport (IWG) meeting papers, 1998-2000; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Personal items (pins, flags, plaques), 1955-1999 (Box 3)
  - "Option #7445: Sports and Society" audio film recording, approximately 1980-2000 (Box 3)
  - Sports psychology papers, 1995-2003; 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 4)
  - Psychology service procedural manual, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Various publications on women's sports, 1990-2002; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Title IX materials, 1975-2002; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Notes, correspondence, email printouts, 1986-2003 (Box 4)
  - Workshop notes and responses, 1985-1995 (Box 4)
  - Research on women in sport and education, 1985; 3 folders (3 folders in one) (Box 4)
  - Transcripts and vitae, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Personal papers, correspondence, travel information, work evaluations, pamphlets, 1965-2002; 9 folders 9 folders (7 regular, 2 legal) (Box 5)
  - Diplomas and awards, 1961, 1964, 1969, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1964-1992 (Box 5)
  - Printed photographs and negatives, 1980-2000; 8 folders (8 photo folders) (Box 5)
    photographs; Negatives
  - Photo album compiled by Carole Oglesby, 1986 (Box 5)
  - United States Olympic Committee papers, 1984-2000; 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 6)
  - Encyclopedia of Women and Sport photos and letters, 1998; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - AAHPERD papers, 2001-2002 (Box 6)
  - National Association of Girls and Women in Sport (NAGWS) papers, April 1985 (Box 6)
  - Junior tennis conference, Oct. 19-21, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Various research and organization materials (history, sport issues, education, rowing), 1984-1998; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Email printouts, 1993-2003; 13 folders (13 folders) (Box 7)
  - Notes and correspondence, 1980-2003; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Various publications, 1980-2002; 4 folders (4 folders); 2 items (2 booklets) (Box 8)
  - Programs for the World University Games and Girls Clubs of America, 1985-1988; 3 folders (Two binders and one folder) (Box 8)
  - Newspaper clippings related to various sports, 1984-1996 (Box 8)
  - Temple University graduate program (HPERD), faculty, and class information, 1983-1990; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous sports-related papers: notes, presentations, pamphlets, 1983-1985; 1 folders (1 folder) (Box 9)
  - Teaching conference and organization materials, 1986-2000; 7 folders (7 folders) (Box 9)
  - Scientific articles (psychology), 1966-1990; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - "Women's Leadership in Sports" drafts, research, correspondence, 2000 (Box 10)
  - UMass opinions of women athletes study, 1974; Study conducted by Carole Oglesby for UMass on Temple University varsity athletes (Box 10)
  - Psychology studies for class use and notes, 1993; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - Biological feedback, questionnaires, articles, 1975-1986; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - "Sporting Chance" teaching equipment by the Girls Clubs of America, Inc., 1986; Includes slides, worksheets, and an audio tape for educational purposes. (Box 10)